FITSUM DUMESSA

DATA ANALYST

615-720-3123 helimili@gmail.com github.com/fdumessa linkedin.com/in/fitsum-dumessa

DATA ANALYST PROFILE

I have always loved numbers and solving problems by using mathematical and scientific formulas. Having spent the last several years leveraging my accounting degree by solving problems, I am excited to use my data analytics skills and tools to contribute in an organization to inform and make a strategic business decisions.

CAPSTONE PROJECT

"Building Permits Issued in Nashville"

- By using Python and Excel to clean up and explore the data, created an interactive story telling on Tableau to answer what type of permits and total construction cost of the building permits have been approved and issued by Metro Codes in Nashville over a rolling threeyear period (2017-2020).
- https://public.tableau.com/profile/fitsum. dumessa

TOOLS AND SKILLS

- SQL
- Excel
- Python
- Tableau
- PowerBI

EDUCATION

Nashville Software School

Data Analytics Bootcamp, 2020

Middle Tennessee State University

B.A. in Accounting, 2012

Nashville State Community College

A.A. in Information Technology, 2009

DATA EXPERIENCE

APPRENTICE DATA ANALYST

Nashville Software School January 2020 - Present

- Six -month intensive data analytics course focused on different real life data projects by using different kinds of tools like SQL, Python, Excel, Tableau, and Power BI
- Communicate the results through creating dashboards, organizing reports, storytelling and presentations

DATA PROJECTS

SQL Project: "Apps Trader"

- By applying SQL tools, come up to the top 10 lists of apps that help the company to make an informed decision to buy a profitable and successful apps by comparing and evaluating price, content, genre and rating
- As a team, determined the formula based on principles of accounting to get a net profit, then started to answer each part of the formula to give the right suggestion

Excel Project: "Low Income and Elderly Assistance Grants"

 Created an interactive dashboard for Hand Up America using Excel functions like Offset, V lookup, Pivot table, slicing, graphs and others;

the data came from the 2016 IRS individual tax return data for all 50 states to come up with the best suggestion who should get the assistance grant

WORK EXPERIENCE

FORT SILL NATIONAL BANK Operation Representative 2016-2017

- Processed journal entries and performing transactions based on GAAP
- Responsible for managing and maintaining all individual accounts by ensuring that payments are received and applied to all accounts

H & R BLOCK Certified Tax professional 2013-2016

- Worked with individual and self employed clients to analyze tax documents, determine deductions and credits, and prepare both federal and state tax
- Analyzed customer's documents to get the most available deductions and credits

HOSKINS & COMPANY Certified Public Accountants Audit Assistant (Internship) 2013-2014

- Analyzed financial reports prepared by other different organizations
- Performed analytical procedure to detect unusual financial statement relationships